# 哈喽，大家好我是王刚
Hello everyone, I am Wang Gang.
# 在这个城里面，已经有十多二十天没有回（老）家了
I've been staying in the city for around 10-20 days without going to my family house of my home village.
# 今天回去看一下我四伯
Today I will go back and visit my Uncle.
# 这段时间，我四伯也没有去赶场卖肉
During these days, my uncle hasn't been the market to sell pork either.
# 十多二十天没开车，现在都有点生疏了
10-20 days of not driving, I am feeling a little bit rusty.
# 特别是戴上这个口罩
Especially when I am wearing this face mask..
# 我感觉我有点缺氧
I am feeling somewhat suffocating.
# 现在也不知道我四伯那里有没有设卡（点）
Right now I don't even know if there is a check point established at my Uncle's (village).
# 还不知道进不进得去
Still not sure if I could go in or not.
# 不过应该没问题吧
...but at the same time, there shouldn't be a problem (I hope)...
# 因为是我老家我回自己祖屋应该没问题
Because that is my hometown, if I go back to my family house, shouldn't be a problem.
# 进应该是进得去
I should be allowed entry (of the village).
# 现在我们乡下还是没有什么车
Now in the country, there are still few cars on the road.
# 平时的话，像现在，应该在堵车
Usually, there is a traffic jam during this time of day.
# 然后排队通过
Cars go through here slowly bumper to bumper.
# 好了，我们现在已经到了乡村小道了
OK, now we are on the country road.
# 现在这个菜籽都开花了
Now the rapeseed flowers are blooming.
# 好漂亮啊
It is so pretty!
# 哦，在前面这个卡点设在前面
OK，there is a check point ahead.
# 也拉了横幅
There is also a banner....
# 我估计车的话，要停在外面进不去了
I suppose I have to park the car outside of the check point.
# 现在下去问一下
Let me ask them.
# 师傅我想把车停里面
Sir, I want to park my car inside.
# 咹？
What (are you talking about)?
# 我想把车停里面
I want to park my car inside.
# 你到哪里去嘛
Where are you heading to?
# 我就是张家湾的
I am a native of ZhangJiaWan (village name).
# 你是张家湾的？对
Are you a native of ZhangJiaWan? (Sure.)
# 努力沟通中
(much communication going on)
# 我伯爷都出来接我来了
Even my uncle came to the check point to meet up with me.
# 外来人员不得进入
No outsiders are permitted of entry.
# 四伯爷，（我）给你拿了点水果下来
Uncle, I bring some fruit for you.
# 你拿起来，我还不是（喝）干了
You bring me some hard drinking alcohol? You know I would just finish it.
# 拿瓶酒给你喝，你呆屋头无聊
The drinks are for your long isolation days at home, I know you must be bored.
# 我还敢喝酒
I really shouldn't be drinking.
# 要得嘛，我慢慢晕（喝）嘛
Well, that's ok, I guess I could drink it slowly....
# 我给你找了个口罩，只有一个，你拿倒，将就用
I brought you a face mask, just one, you can use it for now.
# 屋头有， 还有几个
I have a few at home.
# 要的，戴倒，拿都给你拿起来了
OK, wear it now, I have brought it all the way here.
# 我都还有四五个
I have 4 or 5 myself.
# 戴倒嘛，四伯爷
Wear it now, Uncle.
# 要得呀
Fine.
# 我来戴
Let me put it on it for you.
# 我学会（戴口罩）了。这个东西你提到嘛
I have learnt how to put a mask on, just help me carrying these bags for now.
# 过年到现在还没来的（看你）呀? 没有.
Has ... visited you yet since the Chinese New Year? Not yet.
# 今年还没（回来过）
... hasn't been back this year.
# 走下巴那里两根一起
Get into it from the chin, then lift the 2 strings.
# 我就是一哈就搞定
I can get it done in no time.
# 上面套下去也可以
It can also be worn from downside.
# 走这后面套进去
Get into it from the back.
# 我是这样戴的你看嘛
You see, this is how I wear it.
# 这个往下面
This string should be placed on the lower side.
# 这个放下面 一个挂耳朵上
This should be placed on the bottom, the other one hangs on the ear.
# 哦对
Yes, that is right.
# 我还是学会了的
I had learnt it.
# 鼻子还露在外面的，不得行
You nose should not be left outside of the mask.
# 这个拉起来就是了
It's fine, just pull it up.
# 拉起来给它按一下就贴紧了
Pull it up a little then press it down firmly here, it will snug to the face nicely.
# 往里面按一下
Press down a little like this.
# 就是撒， 就来了，合（适）了，是不是嘛？
That is right! It fits perfectly, isn't it?
# 四伯爷，那这个东西拿给你（了），我就先走了
Uncle, since you've received my gifts, I'll head back to the city now.
# 那你等到，我回去给你挖几颗菜出来嘛
Wait for me here, I'll go get some veggies for you.
# 也可以，现在青菜也不好买
That is nice. Veggies are short of supply these days in the city.
# 你的口罩戴归一（好）点
Wear your mask better,
# 这个稍微往下面按一下
press it down with some pressure here.
# 那我在这里等你嘛
I will be waiting for you here.
# 要的我去给你挖过来
Ok, I will go dig some veggies for you.
# 好
Great.
# 现在这个卡点卡在这里
I am now getting stopped here at the village's check point.
# 我们最好不去串门
It is better that we don't visit other people.
# 在卡点外面等我四伯回去给我弄点青菜
I'm waiting outside of the check point, waiting for my uncle to get some green veggies for me from his home garden.
# 扯好多哦四伯爷
That is a lot of (veggies), Uncle.
# 这不见得很多
Not much at all.
# 这还不见得很多 掉了
It is so much, some are falling off my hands.
# 这么多芹菜
So much (Chinese) celery.
# 放车里面
Put them in your car.
# 吃完了过后又来（挖菜）
When it is finished, come back and get s'more.
# 好
OK.
# 四伯爷这个时候猪肉好多钱一斤
Uncle, what is the market price for pork these days?
# 35（元一斤）
35 (Chinese RMB/500grams, about 1.1lbs)
# 乡头35城里38、40
In the town, 35. In the city, 38 or 40.
# 成都卖45
The price in Chengdu (provincial capital city) is 45.
# 是不是有史以来最高的一次
Is it the most historically high?
# 历史以来活上一百岁的人没吃过这么贵的猪肉
Even people who are more than 100 yrs old says the pork price has never been this high.
# 要得四伯爷我就拿起走了
Uncle, I will thank for your veggies and go home now.
# 要得
That is fine.
# 好了现在准备回家了
OK, now I am getting ready to head back home.
# 四伯在这里送我
My uncle is seeing me off here at the check point.
# 开车慢点哈
Drive slowly okay?
# 走了四伯爷
I am leaving now, Uncle.
# 好拜拜
OK, bye bye.
# 嗯拜拜
Alright, bye bye.
# 过几天再下来
I will be coming this way in a few days
# 再下来弄青菜
to get some more vegetables.
# 回到兜山（老家）被卡点卡住
I was stopped (visiting uncle) at the village check point.
# 因为像刚刚领导也说了
Because like just now the village chief has emphasized
# 这个疫情的严重性
this recent pandemic is seriously bad,
# 现在不能够走家串户也不能走亲戚
for now, we can not visit our neighborhood or relatives.
# 回家的话要想拿点东西让亲人拿到卡点来
If someone wants to get something from their family house, just ask a family member brings it to the village check point.
# 不过这样也好
but this practice is ok as well.
# 为了防止这个疫情扩散嘛
in order to prevent the virus spread out.
# 我自己回自己的老家居然被拦下来了
I still can't believe I was stopped while visiting my own family house.
# 我刚开始以为可以进去的
I thought I could get in.
# 就是要通行证嘛（我没有）
They require a pass (which I don't have).
# 回趟老家没回到自己家里面去
Went back hometown but didn't get to visit my family's house...
# 等这个疫情好一些有好转了
As soon as the epidemic gets somewhat better,
# 就是彻底断根（结束）之后
I mean, when it is completely gone.
# 我们再进行一些
Then we can do something like
# 走亲戚呀走访啊不是走访
visiting relatives...interview...uh, not interview
# 就是
I meant
# 客串 串门
visiting others
# 久了没出门话都说不清楚了
I haven't left my house for so long, I can't talk clearly now.
# 好了本期视频就到这里了
OK, that is all for this episode.
# 我们农村也还是（管控）这么严格
Even in the country the management is very strict,
# 挺好的
that is really nice.